Every weekend for as long as I can remember,
في كل عطلة نهاية الأسبوع، كما تسعفني ذاكرتي
my father would get up on a Saturday,
كان والدي يستيقظ كل يوم سبت
put on a worn sweatshirt
فيرتدي قميصاً بالياً يفوح عرقاً
and he'd scrape away
فيكشط المنزل المتهالك
at the squeaky old wheel of a house that we lived in.
الذي كنا نعيش فيه
I wouldn't even call it restoration;
ولن أسمي ما كان يفعله بالترميم
it was a ritual, catharsis.
بل كانت طقساً يفعله للتنفيس عما بداخله
He would spend all year scraping paint with this old heat gun
كان يقضي كل السنة بتقشير الدهان بمسدس التسخين
and a spackle knife,
والمكشطة
and then he would repaint where he scraped,
وبعد ذلك سيطلي بالدهان ما قد كشط
only to begin again the following year.
ليكرر الأمر مرة أخرى السنة التي تليها
Scraping and re-scraping, painting and repainting:
تقشير الدهان مرة تلو الأخرى وصبغ الجدار بالدهان مرة تلو الأخرى
the work of an old house is never meant to be done.
وهكذا فترميم المنزل لن يكتمل أبداً
The day my father turned 52, I got a phone call.
في عيد ميلاد أبي 52، جائني اتصال
My mother was on the line
كانت والدتي هي المتصلة
to tell me that doctors had found a lump in his stomach --
لتخبرني أن الأطباء اكتشفوا ورماً في معدته
terminal cancer, she told me,
أخبرتني أنه سرطان في مراحلة الأخيرة
and he had been given only three weeks to live.
وأخبروه أن أمامه ثلاثة أسابيع فقط ليعيشها
I immediately moved home to Poughkeepsie, New York,
فانتقلت على الفور إلى بيكيبسي في نيويورك
to sit with my father on death watch,
لأقضي وقتي مع والدي وهو يحتضر
not knowing what the next days would bring us.
جاهلاً ما ستأتي به الأيام القادمة
To keep myself distracted,
ولأبقي نفسي مشتتاً،
I rolled up my sleeves,
عملت بجد
and I went about finishing what he could now no longer complete --
فقررت إنهاء ما لن يستطيع إكماله الآن،
the restoration of our old home.
ترميم منزلنا القديم
When that looming three-week deadline came
وعندما حل الموعد الذي حدده الأطباء
and then went,
وانتهت الأسابيع الثلاثة
he was still alive.
ما زال حيّاً
And at three months,
وبعد ثلاثة أشهر،
he joined me.
انضم إليّ
We gutted and repainted the interior.
فأزلنا الطلاء من على الجدران الداخلية للمنزل وأعدنا صبغه
At six months, the old windows were refinished,
وبعد ستة أشهر، أعدنا ترميم النوافذ القديمة
and at 18 months,
وبعد مُضيّ 18 شهر،
the rotted porch was finally replaced.
استبدلنا، أخيرً، الشرفة المتهالكة
And there was my father,
وهناك كان والدي،
standing with me outside, admiring a day's work,
واقفاً معي في الخارج، معجباً بما عملناه
hair on his head, fully in remission,
نما شعره مرة أخرى، ولا يبدوا أنه كان مريضاً بالسرطان
when he turned to me and he said,
عندما التفت إليّ قائلاً :
"You know, Michael,
"هل تعلم، يا مايكل،
this house saved my life."
هذا المنزل أنقذ حياتي."
So the following year, I decided to go to architecture school.
لذا السنة المقبلة، قررت أن أدخل كلية الهندسة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But there, I learned something different about buildings.
لكن هناك، تعلمت شيئًا مختلفاً عن البنيان
Recognition seemed to come
يبدو أن شهرة المهندس تعتمد على من
to those who prioritized novel and sculptural forms,
يهتم ببناء الأشكال الفنية غير المألوفة
like ribbons, or ...
كالشرائط، أو ...
pickles?
المُخللاّت؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I think this is supposed to be a snail.
وأظن أن هذا من المفترص أن يكون حلزوناً.
Something about this bothered me.
وأزعجني ذلك بنحو أو بآخر
Why was it that the best architects, the greatest architecture --
لماذا كان أفضل المهندسين المعماريين، المهندسين العظماء ...
all beautiful and visionary and innovative --
الذين يصممون مباني جميلة وحالمة ومبتكرة
is also so rare,
كانوا أيضاً نادرين
and seems to serve so very few?
ويخدمون قلّة قليلة؟
And more to the point:
ولأصل لنقطتي التي أريد توضيحها:
With all of this creative talent, what more could we do?
مع كل هذه الموهبة المبدعة، ما الذي نستطيع فعله أكثر من مجرد ذلك؟
Just as I was about to start my final exams,
عندما اقتربت امتحاناتي النهائية،
I decided to take a break from an all-nighter
قررت أن أأخذ استراحة من سهري طوال الليل للمذاكرة
and go to a lecture by Dr. Paul Farmer,
وأذهب لمحاضرة يلقيها د. بول فارمر
a leading health activist for the global poor.
ناشط رائد بما يخص صحة الفقراء حول العالم
I was surprised to hear a doctor talking about architecture.
لقد كنت متفاجئًا بسماع طبيب يتحدث عن الهندسة المعمارية
Buildings are making people sicker, he said,
قال: المباني تزيد من مرض الناس
and for the poorest in the world,
وخصوصاً اولئك الفقراء المدقعين
this is causing epidemic-level problems.
فإنها تسبب لهم الاوبئة
In this hospital in South Africa,
في هذا المستشفى في جنوب أفريقيا،
patients that came in with, say, a broken leg,
المريض الذي يأتي ليعالج ساقه المكسورة
to wait in this unventilated hallway,
وينتظر في هذا الممر المكتوم (غير المهوّى)
walked out with a multidrug-resistant strand of tuberculosis.
يخرج من هنا بالعديد من الأدوية لمقاومة مرض السُلَ
Simple designs for infection control had not been thought about,
لم يفكر أحد بتطبيق التصاميم البسيطة التي تساعد على مقاومة الأمراض المعدية
and people had died because of it.
التي يموت الناس بسببها
"Where are the architects?" Paul said.
تساءل بول:"أين المهندسين المعماريين؟"
If hospitals are making people sicker,
إذا كانت المستشفيات تزيد المرضى مرضاً،
where are the architects and designers
فأين المهندسيين ومصممي الديكور
to help us build and design hospitals that allow us to heal?
ليساعدونا ببناء وتصميم مستشفيات تسمح لنا بمعالجتهم؟
That following summer,
في الصيف القادم،
I was in the back of a Land Rover with a few classmates,
كنت جالساً في الخلف في سيارة لاند روفر مع عدداً من زملائي
bumping over the mountainous hillside of Rwanda.
مصطدمين بالمنحدرات الجبلية المشهورة بها دولة رواندا.
For the next year, I'd be living in Butaro in this old guesthouse,
ولسنة كاملة، عشت في مدينة بوتارو في بيت الضيافة القديم هذا
which was a jail after the genocide.
الذي كان سجناً بعد الإبادة الجماعية.
I was there to design and build a new type of hospital
كنت هناك لأصمم وأبني نوعاً جديداً من المستشفيات
with Dr. Farmer and his team.
بمساعدة د.فارمر وفريقه.
If hallways are making patients sicker,
إذا كانت ممرات المشفى تزيد المرضى مرضاً
what if we could design a hospital that flips the hallways on the outside,
فماذا لو استطعنا تصميم مستشفى تكون ممراته تطل على المناظر الخارجية
and makes people walk in the exterior?
فنجعل الناس يتنزهون فيها؟
If mechanical systems rarely work,
إذا كانت المكيفات الهوائية لا تعمل إلا نادراً،
what if we could design a hospital that could breathe
فماذا لو أمكننا بناء مستشفى حيث يتم تهويته
through natural ventilation,
عن طريق الطبيعة الخلابة
and meanwhile reduce its environmental footprint?
وفي الوقت عينه نقلل من أضرار المكيفات الهوائية على البيئة؟
And what about the patients' experience?
وماذا عن تجربة المرضى؟
Evidence shows that a simple view of nature
أظهرت الدلائل أن رؤية جزء من الطبيعة
can radically improve health outcomes,
يمكنه أن يحسن تحسناً جذرياً من صحة المريض،
So why couldn't we design a hospital
لذا لماذا لا نستطيع تصميم مستشفى
where every patient had a window with a view?
حيث يمكن لكل مريض أن تطل نافذة غرفته على الطبيعة الخلابة؟
Simple, site-specific designs can make a hospital that heals.
التصاميم البسيطة المرتبطة بمكان معين بحد ذاته يمكنها خلق مستشفى يعالج المرضى.
Designing it is one thing;
التصميم هو أمر مستقل بذاته،
getting it built, we learned, is quite another.
وتطبيقه، كما تعلمنا، هو أمر آخر تقريباً
We worked with Bruce Nizeye,
عملنا مع بروس نيزاي
a brilliant engineer,
مهندس بارع
and he thought about construction differently
وكان رأيه عن انشاء المباني مختلفاً
than I had been taught in school.
عما تعلمته في الجامعة.
When we had to excavate this enormous hilltop
عندما أردنا حفر قمّة ضخمة لأحد الهضاب
and a bulldozer was expensive and hard to get to site,
وكان حفرها بالجرافة مكلّفاً ويصعب المجيء بها إلى الموقع
Bruce suggested doing it by hand,
اقترح بروس أن نعمل ذلك يدوياً
using a method in Rwanda called "Ubudehe,"
مستخدماً طريقة متبعة في رواندا تدعى ب"أوبديهي"
which means "community works for the community."
وتعني "المجتمع يعمل من أجل المجتمع"
Hundreds of people came with shovels and hoes,
مئات من الناس قدموا حاملين مجارفهم ومعاولهم.
and we excavated that hill
وحفرنا تلك الهضبة
in half the time and half the cost of that bulldozer.
بنصف الوقت والتكلفة مقارنةً بما ستكلفه وتستغرقه الجرافة
Instead of importing furniture, Bruce started a guild,
وبدلاً من استيراد الأثاث، شكّل بروس نقابة
and he brought in master carpenters to train others
فأحضر نجارين خبراء لتدريب الآخرين
in how to make furniture by hand.
على كيفية صنع الأثاث يدويّاً
And on this job site,
وفي موقع العمل هذا،
15 years after the Rwandan genocide,
15 سنة بعد الإبادة الجماعية لأهل رواندا
Bruce insisted that we bring on labor from all backgrounds,
أصرّ بروس أن نأتي بالأيدي العاملة من مختلف الخلفيات،
and that half of them be women.
وأن يكون نصفهم من النساء.
Bruce was using the process of building to heal,
كان بروس يستخدم طريقة البناء من أجل الشفاء،
not just for those who were sick,
ليس من أجل اولئك المرضى فقط،
but for the entire community as a whole.
بل للمجتمع ككل.
We call this the locally fabricated way of building, or "lo-fab,"
ونسمَّي تلك الطريقة بالطريقة المحلية الإبداعية للبناء، أو "لو-فاب"
and it has four pillars:
وتتكون من أربع نقاط:
hire locally,
وظف محليّاً
source regionally,
اجعل مصادرك من منطقتك
train where you can
درَّب أينما تستطيع
and most importantly,
والأهم من ذلك كله
think about every design decision as an opportunity
فكر بكل قرار يتعلق بالتصميم كفرصة
to invest in the dignity of the places where you serve.
لاستثمار هويّة الأماكن التي ساعدت في بنائها
Think of it like the local food movement,
فكروا بها كحركة الطعام المحلي،
but for architecture.
لكنها للهندسة المعمارية
And we're convinced that this way of building
ونحن مقتنعون أن طريقة البناء تلك
can be replicated across the world,
يمكن تطبيقها في مختلف أنحاء العالم
and change the way we talk about and evaluate architecture.
ونغيّر الطريقة التي نتحدث بها ونعرف قيمة البناء.
Using the lo-fab way of building,
باستخدام طريقة لو-فاب للبناء
even aesthetic decisions can be designed to impact people's lives.
حتى القرارات التي تتعلق بالجماليات يمكن تصميمها لتؤثر على حياة الناس
In Butaro, we chose to use a local volcanic stone
في بوتارو، قررنا استخدام حجارة بركان محلي
found in abundance within the area,
التي كانت توجد بكثرة في المنطقة،
but often considered a nuisance by farmers,
لكن عادة ما يسبب ذلك إزعاجاً للمزارعين،
and piled on the side of the road.
ونجمعها بجانب الطريق.
We worked with these masons to cut these stones
عملنا مع عمّال البناء كي يقطعوا الحجارة
and form them into the walls of the hospital.
وشكلناها حتى أصبحت جداراً للمستشفى
And when they began on this corner
وعندما بدأوا بذلك في هذه الزاوية
and wrapped around the entire hospital,
وأكملوا بناء المستشفى كله
they were so good at putting these stones together,
كانوا ماهرين في وضع تلك الحجارة سويّاً
they asked us if they could take down the original wall and rebuild it.
سألونا إذا كان يمكننا هدم الجدار الأصلي وبناءه مرة أخرى
And you see what is possible.
وترون ما الممكن أن يفعله المرء
It's beautiful.
إنه جميل
And the beauty, to me,
والجمال، بالنسبة لي،
comes from the fact that I know that hands cut these stones,
ينبع من حقيقة أنني أعرف الأيدي التي شكلت تلك الحجارة
and they formed them into this thick wall,
وجعلتها جداراً سميكاً
made only in this place with rocks from this soil.
مصنوعاً من هذا المكان وحده من حجارة من هذه التربة.
When you go outside today and you look at your built world,
عندما تتمشى خارجاً اليوم وتتأمل البنيان من حولك
ask not only:
لا تسأل فقط عن:
"What is the environmental footprint?" -- an important question --
"ما هو المجال البيئي المستحوذ عليه؟" وهو سؤال مهم -- لكن
but what if we also asked,
ما الضير أن نسأل أيضاً
"What is the human handprint of those who made it?"
" ما هي البصمة الإنسانية التي خلّفها اولئك الذين صنعوه؟"
We started a new practice based around these questions,
بدأنا ممارسة جديدة مبنية على هذه الاسئلة،
and we tested it around the world.
فأجرينا اختباراً في انحاء مختلفة من العالم
Like in Haiti,
مثلاً في هايتي
where we asked if a new hospital could help end the epidemic of cholera.
حيث سألنا إذا كان هناك مشفى جديد يمكنه أن ينهي وباء الكوليرا
In this 100-bed hospital,
في هذا المشفى المحتوي على 100 سرير
we designed a simple strategy
انشأنا استراتيجية بسيطة
to clean contaminated medical waste before it enters the water table,
لننظف النفايات الطبية الملوثة قبل أن تدخل الأرض وتختلط بالمياة الجوفية
and our partners at Les Centres GHESKIO
وشركاؤنا في لي سينتراي جيسكيو
are already saving lives because of it.
من قبل هذا وهم ينقذون الأرواح بسببه
Or Malawi:
أو في مالاوي:
we asked if a birthing center could radically reduce
سألنا إذا كان وجود مركز للولادة يمكن أن يقلل جذرياً
maternal and infant mortality.
من معدل وفيات الحوامل والرضع.
Malawi has one of the highest rates of maternal and infant death
تعد مالاوي من الدول التي لديها معدل وفيات مرتفع للحوامل وأطفالهن
in the world.
في العالم
Using a simple strategy to be replicated nationally,
وباستخدام استراتيجية بسيطة للتكاثر الوطني
we designed a birthing center
صممنا مركزاً للولادة
that would attract women and their attendants
بحيث يجذب النساء ومن يزورهن
to come to the hospital earlier and therefore have safer births.
كي يتابعوا حملهم في المستشفى، وبالتالي يخضعن لتوليد آمن.
Or in the Congo, where we asked
أو في كونغو، حيث سألنا
if an educational center could also be used
إن كان وجود مركزاً تعليمياً يمكن أيضاً استخدامه
to protect endangered wildlife.
لحمايتهم من الحياة الوحشية معرّضتهم للمخاطر
Poaching for ivory and bushmeat
فالصيد من أجل العاج وصيد الطرائد
is leading to global epidemic, disease transfer and war.
يؤدي إلى أوبئة عالمية ونقل الأمراض والحرب.
In one of the hardest-to-reach places in the world,
ومن أصعب الأماكن التي يمكن الوصول إليها في العالم،
we used the mud and the dirt and the wood around us
استخدمنا الطين والأوساخ والأخشاب التي حولنا
to construct a center
لبناء مركز
that would show us ways to protect and conserve our rich biodiversity.
يظهر لنا طرقاً نحمي بها حياتنا الغنية المختلفة عن بعضها البعض والمحافظة عليها.
Even here in the US,
حتى هنا في الولايات المتحدة،
we were asked to rethink
طلب منّا أن نصمم حرم جامعي
the largest university for the deaf and hard of hearing in the world.
لأكبر جامعة في العالم للبكم وصعاب السمع.
The deaf community, through sign language,
مجتمع البكم، من خلال لغة الإشارة
shows us the power of visual communication.
يرينا قوة التواصل البصري.
We designed a campus that would awaken the ways
فصممنا مدينة جامعية توعيّنا وتفتح لنا طرقاً
in which we as humans all communicate,
يتواصل فيها جميع البشر من مختلف المجتمعات
both verbally and nonverbally.
شفهياً ولا شفهياً (بلغة الإشارة)
And even in Poughkeepsie, my hometown,
وحتى في بيكيبسي، رأس مولدي،
we thought about old industrial infrastructure.
تفكّرنا بالبنية التحتية الصناعية القديمة.
We wondered:
وتسائلنا:
Could we use arts and culture and design to revitalize this city
هل يمكننا استخدام الفنون والثقافة والتصميم لاحياء المدينة
and other Rust Belt cities across our nation,
ومدن رست بَلت الأخرى عبر الولايات
and turn them into centers for innovation and growth?
ونحولها إلى مراكز من أجل الإبتكار والتنمية؟
In each of these projects, we asked a simple question:
وفي كل من هذه المشاريع، سألنا سؤال بسيط:
What more can architecture do?
ما الذي يستطيع فعله المهندس أكثر من ذلك؟
And by asking that question,
وبطرح ذلك السؤال:
we were forced to consider how we could create jobs,
كنا ملزمين بأن نضع بعين الاعتبار كيف يمكننا طرح الوظائف،
how we could source regionally
كيف يمكننا جعل مصادرنا محلية
and how we could invest in the dignity of the communities
وكيف يمكننا استثمار كرامة مجتمعاتنا
in which we serve.
التي نخدمها.
I have learned
تعلمت
that architecture can be a transformative engine for change.
أن المهندسين المعمارين يمكن أن يكونوا محركات محولة للتغير.
About a year ago, I read an article
فمنذ سنة، قرأت مقالة
about a tireless and intrepid civil rights leader
عن زعيم شجاع للحقوق المدنية لا يكل ولا يمل
named Bryan Stevenson.
اسمه برايان ستيفينسون
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And Bryan had a bold architectural vision.
ولدى برايان رؤية معمارية جريئة
He and his team had been documenting
فقد وثق هو وفريقه حالات الإعدام
the over 4,000 lynchings of African-Americans
من غير محاكمه التي تفوق 4000 حكم الصادرة بحق الأمريكيين الأفارقة
that have happened in the American South.
التي حصلت في الجنوب الأمريكي.
And they had a plan to mark every county where these lynchings occurred,
ويخططون أن يشيروا إلى كل مقاطعة حصلت فيها هذه الإعدامات
and build a national memorial to the victims of lynching
ويبنوا نصباً تذكارياً قومياً لضحايا هذه الإعدامات
in Montgomery, Alabama.
في مونتغومري، ألاباما
Countries like Germany and South Africa
فدول مثل دولة ألمانيا وجنوب أفريقيا
and, of course, Rwanda,
وبالطبع، دولة رواندا
have found it necessary to build memorials
اعتبروا أنه من الضروري بناء النصب التذكارية
to reflect on the atrocities of their past,
ليعسكوا الأعمال الوحشية لماضيهم
in order to heal their national psyche.
لكي يعالجوا روحهم الوطنية
We have yet to do this in the United States.
ويجب علينا فعل ذلك في الولايات المتحدة
So I sent a cold email to info@equaljusticeintiative.org:
لذا أرسلت رسالة إلكترونية قاسية إلى nfo@equaljusticeintiative.org:
"Dear Bryan," it said,
مكتوبة كالآتي: "عزيزي برايان،"
"I think your building project
" أظن أن مشروعك البنياني
is maybe the most important project we could do in America
ربما يكون أهم مشروع يمكننا فعله في أمريكا
and could change the way we think about racial injustice.
ويمكن أن يغير طريقة تفكيرنا حول الظلم العرقي.
By any chance,
وهل تعرف ولو عن طريق الصدفة
do you know who will design it?"
من سيصممه؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Surprisingly, shockingly,
ويا للمفاجأة والصدمة
Bryan got right back to me,
رد علي برايان
and invited me down to meet with his team and talk to them.
ودعاني لمقابلة فريقه وتحدث معي
Needless to say, I canceled all my meetings
ولا يجب على أن أقول أنني ألغيت كل اجتماعاتي
and I jumped on a plane to Montgomery, Alabama.
وحجزت أقرب رحلة تذهب إلى مونتغمري، ألاباما.
When I got there,
وعندما وصلت هناك،
Bryan and his team picked me up, and we walked around the city.
استقبلني برايان وفريقه وتنزهنا في المدينة.
And they took the time to point out
وأخذوا وقتهم كي يخبروني أن العديد من المعالم
the many markers that have been placed all over the city
التي حُدّدت أماكنها في أنحاء مختلفة من المدينة
to the history of the Confederacy,
تشير إلى تاريخ التحالف
and the very few that mark the history of slavery.
والقليل منها يشير إلى تاريخ العبودية.
And then he walked me to a hill.
ثم أخذني إلى تلة
It overlooked the whole city.
تطل على المدينة بكاملها
He pointed out the river and the train tracks
وأشار على النهر وسكك القطار، حيث كان الميناء
where the largest domestic slave-trading port in America
المصدر الأكبر محلياً لتجارة العبيد في أمريكا
had once prospered.
التي كانت مزدهرة حينها.
And then to the Capitol rotunda,
ثم أراني كابيتل روندا
where George Wallace had stood on its steps
الذي وقف جورج والس على عتباته
and proclaimed, "Segregation forever."
وصرح:" التمييز العرقي للأبد"
And then to the very hill below us.
وبعدها أشار إلى التلة التي تقع
He said, "Here we will build a new memorial
أسفلنا مباشرة قال:"هنا سنبني نصباً تذكارياً جديداً
that will change the identity of this city and of this nation."
الذي سيغير هويّة هذه المدينة وشعبها."
Our two teams have worked together over the last year
عمل فريقينا سويّة خلال العام السابق
to design this memorial.
لتصميم هذا النصب التذكاري.
The memorial will take us on a journey
سيأخذنا النصب التذكاري في رحلة
through a classical, almost familiar building type,
من خلال طراز كلاسيكي من المباني ومألوف إلى حد ما
like the Parthenon or the colonnade at the Vatican.
كبناء البارثنيون أو الكولوناد في الفاتيكان
But as we enter,
لكن ونحن ندخله
the ground drops below us and our perception shifts,
ونمشي على أرضه انتقلنا بحواسنا
where we realize that these columns evoke the lynchings,
واستحضرنا أن هذه الأعمدة تمثل الإعدامات التي حصلت من دون محاكمات
which happened in the public square.
في الميدان العام
And as we continue,
ومع استمرارنا بالتأمل
we begin to understand the vast number
بدأنا نفهم أن عدداً كبيراً
of those who have yet to be put to rest.
من اولئك يجب أن تستريح أرواحهم
Their names will be engraved on the markers that hang above us.
ستنقش أسمائهم على الأوسمة المعلقة فوقنا
And just outside will be a field of identical columns.
وفي الخارج سيكون هناك حقلاً من الأعمدة المتشابهة
But these are temporary columns, waiting in purgatory,
ولكن تلك هي الأعمدة المؤقتة، تنتظر تطهير أرواحها،
to be placed in the very counties where these lynchings occurred.
كي تذهب إلى جميع المفاطعات التي حصلت فيها الإعدامات.
Over the next few years,
وفي السنوات القليلة القادمة،
this site will bear witness,
سيشهد هذا المكان بما حصل
as each of these markers is claimed
حيث كل معلم من هؤلاء يستحق أن يوضع
and visibly placed in those counties.
بشكل يمكن رؤيته في تلك المقاطعات.
Our nation will begin to heal from over a century of silence.
سيبدأ شعبنا بالتعافي من الصمت الذي استغرق أكثر من قرن.
When we think about how it should be built,
حين نفكر بكيف يجب أن يبنى،
we were reminded of Ubudehe,
كنا نتذكر أوبديهي،
the building process we learned about in Rwanda.
وعملية البناء التي تعلمناها في رواندا.
We wondered if we could fill those very columns
تسائلنا عما إن كان بإمكاننا ملء جميع تلك الأعمدة
with the soil from the sites of where these killings occurred.
بتربة تلك الأماكن التي حصل فيها القتل.
Brian and his team have begun collecting that soil
بدأ برايان وفريقه بجمع التربة
and preserving it in individual jars
وحفظها في مرطبانات منفردة
with family members, community leaders and descendants.
بمساعدة أفراد العائلة والمجتمع والقادة والأحفاد.
The act of collecting soil itself
إن عمل جمع التربة بحد ذاته
has lead to a type of spiritual healing.
قاد إلى نوع من المعالجة الروحية
It's an act of restorative justice.
فهو نوع من العدالة الإصلاحية
As one EJI team member noted
وكما أشار أحد أعضاء فريق إي جي آي
in the collection of the soil from where Will McBride was lynched,
أثناء جمع التربة من المكان الذي أعدم فيه ويل مكبرايد
"If Will McBride left one drop of sweat,
"إإذا خلّف ويل مكبرايد قطرة من عرقه،
one drop of blood,
قطرة من دمه،
one hair follicle --
شعرة من شعيراته --
I pray that I dug it up,
أدعو الرب أن أستطيع إيجادها،
and that his whole body would be at peace."
وأدعو أن جسده بأكمله ينعم بالسلام."
We plan to break ground on this memorial later this year,
خططنا أن نكسر القاعدة مع هذا النصب التذكاري لاحقاً في هذه السنة،
and it will be a place to finally speak of the unspeakable acts
فسيكون مكان نتحدث فيه عن الأفعال التي لا يتحدث عنها
that have scarred this nation.
الأفعال التي خلفت جرحاً
(Applause)
وأثراً في هذا الشعب.
When my father told me that day that this house --
عندما أخبرني والدي ذلك اليوم أن هذا المنزل
our house --
منزلنا ...
had saved his life,
أنقذ حياته،
what I didn't know
ما لم أكن أعرفه،
was that he was referring to a much deeper relationship
هو أنه كان يقصد تلك العلاقة العميقة جدّاً
between architecture and ourselves.
بين الهندسة المعمارية وبيننا.
Buildings are not simply expressive sculptures.
المباني ليست عبارة عن منحوتات معبرة فقط
They make visible our personal and our collective aspirations
بل تظهر شخصياتنا و ما يلهمنا
as a society.
كمجتمع.
Great architecture can give us hope.
فالمهندس المعماري العظيم يمدنا بالأمل.
Great architecture can heal.
المهندس المعماري العظيم يمكنه أن يعالجك ويشفيك.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً
(Applause)
تصفيق